Ye Bi February 2024

Contact Information Litton Reaves Hall 175 West Campus Drive Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, Virginia 24061 USA

WWW: yebigithub.github.io

Research Interests I am a Ph.D. candidate in the School of Animal Sciences at Virginia Tech. My research interests focus on incorporating artificial intelligence, computer vision, statistics, phenomics, and genetics to study animal and plant sciences.

E-mail: vebi@vt.edu

Current Research **PROJECTS** 

#### **Precision Livestock Farming**

- Depth video data-enabled predictions of longitudinal dairy cow body weight using thresholding and Mask R-CNN algorithms
- Prediction of pig body weight from depth videos under a commercial setting
- Evaluation of dairy cow body condition scores via computer vision approaches

#### Quantitative Genetics

- Evaluating metabolic and genomic data for predicting grain traits under high night temperature stress in rice
- Genomic prediction for rice grain metabolites under high night temperature stress
- Genetic analysis of high-throughput phenotyping data for sesame

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal Sciences, August 2021 - December 2024 (Expected)

• Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

Graduate Certificate in Data Analytics, January 2024 [URL]

• Completed 15 credits related to advanced data science courses from the Departments of Computer Science, Electrical and Computer Engineering, and Statistics.

#### University of California Davis, Davis, California USA

M.S., Animal Biology, September 2021

- Thesis: "Longitudinal Analysis of CD4 and CD8 T Cell Receptor Repertoires Associated with Newcastle Disease Virus Infection in Layer Birds"
- Advisor: Dr. Huaijun Zhou
- Committee: Drs. Rodrigo A Gallardo and Charles L. Bevins
- Available at UC Davis Libraries.

### Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, Beijing China

M.S., Animal Nutrition and Feed Science, July 2017

- Thesis: "Effects of Dietary Threonine Level on Traits of Peking Ducks from Hatch to 21 Days"
- Advisor: Dr. Benhai Xiong
- Committees: Drs. Shuisheng Hou, Jilan Chen, Taozhen Jiang, and Yu Chen

# Shandong Agricultural University, Taian, Shandong China

B.S., Animal Science, July 2014

- Thesis: "Effect of Rumen Fluid Osmotic Pressure on Absorption of VFAs in Rumen Epithelium of Sheep"
- Advisor: Dr. Yunliang Jiang

2024

Honor and Awards	
2023	$\bullet$ The Summer 2023 Cycle Travel Fund Program (\$300), Graduate and Professional Student Senate, Virginia Tech.
2022	<ul> <li>Modern Programming in Genome to Phenome Scholarship (\$1500), University of California, Davis, CA, August 1-5.</li> <li>27th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 18-27.</li> </ul>
2020	<ul> <li>UC Davis Henry A. Jastro Graduate Research Awards</li> <li>UC Davis Animal Biology Graduate Program Fellowship</li> </ul>
2016	• Academic Scholarship of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences
2015	<ul> <li>Academic Scholarship of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</li> <li>Course Excellence Award of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</li> </ul>
2014	<ul> <li>Academic Scholarship of Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</li> <li>Outstanding Graduate of Shandong Agricultural University</li> </ul>
2013	<ul> <li>Excellent Student Scholarship of Shandong Agricultural University</li> <li>Science and Technology Innovation Scholarship of Shandong Agricultural University</li> </ul>
2012	• Excellent Student Scholarship of Shandong Agricultural University
2011	• Excellent Student Scholarship of Shandong Agricultural University
Manuscripts under preparation	

1. Ye Bi et al. Role of genomics on regulating rice grain metabolic variability under warmer nights:

A statistical and image-based deep learning approach [GitHub]. In prep.

#### Preprints

2024

1. Idan Sabag, Ye Bi, Maitreya Mohan sahoo, Ittai Herrmann, Gota Morota, and Zvi Peleg. Leveraging genomics and temporal high-throughput phenotyping to enhance association mapping and yield prediction in sesame. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2024.02.01.578346

PEER-REVIEWED RESEARCH JOURNAL ARTICLES

2024

11. Kenan Burak Aydin, Ye Bi, Luiz F. Brito, Zafer Ulutaş, and Gota Morota. Review of sheep breeding and genetic research in Türkiye. Frontiers in Genetics. 15:1308113. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2024.1308113

2023

- 10. Ye Bi, Leticia M. Campos, Jin Wang, Haipeng Yu, Mark D. Hanigan, and Gota Morota. Depth video data-enabled predictions of longitudinal dairy cow body weight using thresholding and Mask R-CNN algorithms. Smart Agricultural Technology. 6:100352. doi: 10.1016/j.atech.2023.100352
- 9. Zhangyuan Pan, Ying Wang, Mingshan Wang, Yuzhe Wang, Xiaoning Zhu, Shenwen Gu, Conghao Zhong, Liqi An, Mingzhu Shan, Joana Damas, Michelle M. Halstead, Dailu Guan, Nares Trakooljul, Klaus Wimmers, Ye Bi, Shang Wu, Mary E. Delany, Xuechen Bai, Hans H. Cheng, Congjiao Sun, Ning Yang, Xiaoxiang Hu, Harris A. Lewin, Lingzhao Fang, and Huaijun Zhou. An atlas of regulatory elements in chicken: A resource for chicken genetics and genomics. Science Advance. 9:eade1204(2023). doi: 10.1126/sciadv.ade1204
- 8. Ye Bi, Rafael Massahiro Yassue, Puneet Paul, Balpreet Kaur Dhatt, Jaspreet Sandhu, Thi Phuc Do, Harkamal Walia, Toshihiro Obata, and Gota Morota. 2023. Evaluating metabolic and genomic data for predicting grain traits under high night temperature stress in rice. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics. doi: 10.1093/g3journal/jkad052
- Idan Sabag, Ye Bi, Zvi Peleg, and Gota Morota. 2023. Multi-environment analysis enhances genomic prediction accuracy of agronomic traits in sesame. Frontiers in Genetics. 14:1108416. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2023.1108416

2022

6. Robert Kadlec, Sam Indest, Kayla Castro, Shayan Waqar, Leticia M Campos, Sabrina T Amorim, Ye Bi, Mark D Hanigan, and Gota Morota. 2022. Automated acquisition of top-view dairy cow depth image data using an RGB-D sensor camera. Translational Animal Science. 6:1-6. doi: 10.1093/tas/txac163

2017

- 5. Ye Bi, Xuemei Nan, Shanshan Zheng, Linshu Jiang, Benhai Xiong. Effects of dietary threonine and immune stress on growth performance, carcass trait, serum immune parameters, and intestinal muc2 and NF-kb gene expression in Pekin ducks from hatch to 21 days. *Poultry Science*, 2017, 97(1): 177-187. doi: 10.3382/ps/pex283
- 4. Ye Bi, Hairui Xin, Xiaohua Pan, Benhai Xiong. Effects of dietary threonine level on growth performance, carcass traits, immune function and serum hormone of Peking ducklings. *Chinese Journal of Animal Nutrition*, 2017, 29(6): 1913-1920. doi: link
- 3. Ye Bi, Xiaohua Pan, Hairui Xin, Benhai Xiong. Research progress of the influence of threonine on poultry nutrition[J]. China Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Medicine, 2017, 44(8): 2326-2332. doi: link

2016

- 2. Hairui Xin, Xiaohua Pan, Liang Yang, Ye Bi, Benhai Xiong. Effects of Light Intensity on Performance, Carcass Performance and Meat Quality of Peking Ducks. *Chinese Journal of Animal Nutrition*, 2016, 28(4): 1076-1083. doi: link
- 1. Hairui Xin, Xiaohua Pan, **Ye Bi**, Benhai Xiong, Linshu Jiang. Effects of Lighting Regimes on Production Performance, Carcass Performance and Anti-Oxidant Capacity of the Blood in Peking Ducks. *Journal of Integrative Agriculture*, 2016, 49(23): 4638-4645. doi: link

# CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

2023

Ye Bi. Depth video data-enabled predictions of longitudinal dairy cow body weight using thresholding and Mask R-CNN algorithms. 2023 ASAS-CSAS-WSASAS Annual Meeting. Albuquerque, New Mexico. July 16-20.

#### Intramural Seminars

2023

3. Ye Bi. Depth video data-enabled predictions of longitudinal dairy cow body weight using thresholding and Mask R-CNN algorithms. School of Animal Sciences Research Day. Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, VA. May 16.

2022

- 2. Ye Bi. Utility of Metabolites and Single-Nucleotide Polymorphisms for Classification of High Night Temperature Stress Conditions and Prediction of Grain Size Related Traits in Rice. Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, VA, Sep 09.
- 1. Ye Bi. Evaluating Dairy Cow Body Condition Scores Using Automated Computer Vision Systems. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Day. Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, VA. May 19.

# INVITED PRESENTATIONS

2023

2. Ye Bi. Animal data science applied to digital data. Special Seminar. Smithfield Premium Genetics. Rose Hill, NC. August 14.

2022

1. Ye Bi. Evaluating Dairy Cow Body Condition Scores Using Automated Computer Vision Systems. Department of Animal Science. Shandong Agricultural University. Online. July 22.

#### Posters

2023

**3. Ye Bi.** Depth video data enabled prediction of dairy cow body weight. Virginia Tech Center for Advanced Innovation in Agriculture (CAIA) Big Event. Poster Presentation. March 16.

2022

2. Ye Bi. Development of Automated Computer Vision Systems for Evaluating Dairy Cow Body Weight and Body Condition Scores. ASAS-CSAS 2022 annual meeting, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. Poster Presentation. June 26-30.

1. Ye Bi. Evaluating Dairy Cow Body Condition Scores Using Automated Computer Vision Systems. Virginia Tech Center for Advanced Innovation in Agriculture (CAIA) Big Event. Poster Presentation. March 28.

### PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

2022

- 4. Zhangyuan Pan, Ying Wang, Liqi An, Ye Bi, Dailu Guan, Mary E. Delany, Hans H. Cheng, Huaijun Zhou. Functional annotations of regulatory elements in the chicken genome. *Proceedings of 12th World Congress on Genetics Applied to Livestock Production (WCGALP)*. doi: link
- **3.** Ye Bi, Robert Kadlec, Kayla Castro, Sam Indest, Sabrina Amorim, Gota Morota. Development of Automated Computer Vision Systems for Evaluating Dairy cow Body Weight and Body Condition Scores. ASAS-CSAS 2022 annual meeting, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma. June 26-30. doi: link

2016

- 2. Ye Bi, Hairui Xin, Benhai Xiong. Effects of dietary threonine level on traits of Peking ducks from hatch to 21 days. The 12th National Conference about Animal Nutrition of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine. doi: link
- 1. Hairui Xin, Ye Bi, Benhai Xiong. Effects of Lighting Regimes on Blood Calcium Phosphate Level and Anti-Oxidant Capacity of the Blood in Peking Ducks. The 12th National Conference about Animal Nutrition of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine. doi: link

#### EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES

#### Ad Hoc Reviewer

• Number of manuscripts reviewed per journal: Journal of Animal Science (8), Scientia Agricola (3), Artificial Intelligence in Agriculture (1).

#### Work Experiences

School of Animal Sciences

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

09/2021 - 12/2024

Precision Animal Health Group **Zoetis**, **Inc.**, Kalamazoo, Michigan USA

• Precision Animal Health Data Science Intern

05/2024 - 08/2024

#### Teaching

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

Guest Lectures

• ALS 3104 Animal Breeding and Genetics - April 23rd Use of Genetic Markers in Animal Breeding	$\mathrm{Spring}/2024$
• ALS 3104 Animal Breeding and Genetics - February 28th Statistical Concepts in Quantitative Genetics	${ m Spring}/2023$
Teaching Assistant	
• ALS 3104 Animal Breeding and Genetics	$\mathrm{Spring}/2024$
• ALS 3104 Animal Breeding and Genetics	$\mathrm{Spring}/2023$
• ALS 3104 Animal Breeding and Genetics	${\rm Spring}/2022$
University of California Davis, Davis, California, USA	
Teaching Assistant	
• ANS150 Animal Health and Disease	$\mathrm{Spring}/2020$
• ABI102 Animal Biochemistry and Metabolism	$\mathrm{Fall}/2019$
• Virginia Tech Center for Advanced Innovation in Agriculture(CAIA) Graduate S Group Member October/2	Student Affiliate 2021 - present
	2021 - present f Animal Science nember
<ul> <li>Group Member October/S</li> <li>The 10th National Congress of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of and Veterinary Medicine (CAAV) and the 12th Animal Nutrition Symposium materials.</li> </ul>	2021 - present f Animal Science nember ptember/2017
<ul> <li>Group Member</li> <li>The 10th National Congress of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of and Veterinary Medicine (CAAV) and the 12th Animal Nutrition Symposium of October/2016 - Segon The XXV World's Poultry Congress member</li> <li>September/2016 -</li> <li>The Branch of Animal Information, Chinese Association of Animal Science</li> </ul>	2021 - present  f Animal Science nember ptember/2017  - August/2017
<ul> <li>Group Member</li> <li>The 10th National Congress of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of and Veterinary Medicine (CAAV) and the 12th Animal Nutrition Symposium in October/2016 - Segment September/2016 - Segment September/2016 - The XXV World's Poultry Congress member</li> <li>The Branch of Animal Information, Chinese Association of Animal Science</li> </ul>	f Animal Science member ptember/2017 - August/2017 and Veterinary 5 - June/2016
<ul> <li>Group Member</li> <li>The 10th National Congress of Animal Nutrition Branch of Chinese Association of and Veterinary Medicine (CAAV) and the 12th Animal Nutrition Symposium moctober/2016 - Segontary Congress member</li> <li>The XXV World's Poultry Congress member</li> <li>September/2016 -</li> <li>The Branch of Animal Information, Chinese Association of Animal Science Medicine the 10th Symposium member</li> <li>July/201</li> <li>Modern Programming in Genome to Phenome, University of California, Davis, Genome to Phenome, University of California, D</li></ul>	f Animal Science member ptember/2017 - August/2017 and Veterinary 5 - June/2016 CA, August 1-5,

# Computer Skills

Additional Training

ACTIVITY

- Statistics/Numerical computational tools: R, SAS
- Computer vision and image processing: Python, MATLAB
- $\bullet$  Content-description languages: LATEX

- Operating system: Linux and Mac OS X
- Computer clusters: Slurm workload manager

#### Courses taken

#### Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University

- ECE 6554 Advanced Computer Vision
- CS 5824 Advanced Machine Learning
- ECE 6524 Deep Learning
- ECE 5554 Computer Vision
- CS 5525 Data Analytics I
- STAT 5364G Advanced Statistical Genomics
- ALS 5224 Introduction to Genomic Data Science
- HORT 5304 Advanced Plant Genetics and Breeding

#### University of California Davis

- STA 200B Introduction to Mathematical Statistics I
- GGG 201A Advanced Genetic Analysis
- STA 200A Introduction to Probability Theory
- PMI 270 Advanced Immunology
- PMI 126 Fundamentals of Immunology
- STA 106 Applied Statistical Methods: Analysis of Variance
- PLS 120 Applied Statistics in Agricultural Sciences

## REFERENCES

#### Dr. Gota Morota

Associate Professor, School of Animal Sciences Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA E-mail: morota@vt.edu

# Dr. Mark Hanigan

David R. and Margaret Lincicome Professor of Agriculture, School of Animal Sciences Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA *E-mail:* mhanigan@vt.edu

#### Dr. Jianhua (Jason) Xuan

Professor, Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA *E-mail:* xuan@vt.edu